is obesity a genetic disease
red so that is a very fascinating
question is obesity a genetic disease
and like everything in medicine it's
complicated to me it's a yes and no
because we have to think about monogenic
and polygenic
so yes I'm s first I'm going to say yes
it is it can be a genetic disease
because they have monogen diseases like
PR willly syndrome you have other things
like leptin resistance where it's one
gene that is abnormal and aund of those
patients who have this will have the
phenotype of obesity that's a monogenic
disease this is a real a rare form of
obesity I've seen a couple of cases of
this when I was training at the
University Hospital in
Miami most obesity that we deal with is
polygenic meaning it's not one gene it's
hundreds of genes that interact with
lifestyle and socioeconomic factors to
create obesity so if you have if you see
that in your family people tend to have
overweight or obesity you have a higher
risk of developing this but your genes
pull but we always have to remember that
genes your genetics load the gun the
lifestyle pull the trigger so the
Obesity that we see in most of our
patients is not the one gene monogenic
disease that we see it's a complex
interplay of Lifestyle social economic
engines that can get there so with that
type of
obesity you can prevent it just because
your parents or your family have it you
may not following those footsteps you
control it but here again becomes the
difficult question right because always
we tell our patient come on you can do
better you can eat better you can
exercise a little more you can say no to
those donuts and those poor patients go
home they do it for one day one week
then they go back into the addiction of
food then they resent they have self-
resentment self-hate when they feel like
this they want to eat more they they
they they resent themselves they eat
more so here goes the yo-yo of obesity
and metabolic disease so on those
patients again if I can find something
that interrupts that pathway of food um
addiction we can reverse obesity so is
obesity a disease yes it is a disease we
have an icd10 code now in the US that
designates as a disease is it a
willpower issue yes there is a willpower
issue but what we need to realize is
sometimes you cannot overcome your
willpower with psychology only you need
an improvement of your physiology and
your biology if I improve
your set your your neuros circuitry if I
improve your neural Pathways if I
restore your appetite physiology now I
make it easier for you to make the right
decision so this is to me the
complicated form of of of of dealing
with metabolic disease and obesity
because it's not a simple question of
just use more willpower there is a
biological underpinning a biological
maladaptive phenomenon that's happening
in our brain circuitry that perpetuates
the cycle of obesity and until we
recognize this we'll keep our patients
with obesity in the victimhood mentality
when I give my patients those tools I
Empower them to make the right decision
and I think that's how medicine should
be